on a grand scale. It usually starts with sketches. I was drawing this 60-foot-high, revolving, broadcast-quality portrait of the artist, and then I tore the piece of paper in half. I split the mask to try to access the human underneath it all. And it's one thing to do sketches, but of course translating from a sketch into a tourable revolving six-story building took some exceptional engineers working around the clock for three months, until finally we arrived in Miami and opened the show in April 2016. (Video: Cheers) (Music: "Formation," Beyoncé) Beyoncé: Y'all haters corny with that Illuminati mess Paparazzi, catch my fly, and my cocky fresh I'm so reckless when I rock my Givenchy dress I'm so possessive so I rock his Roc necklaces My daddy Alabama Momma Louisiana You mix that negro with that Creole make a Texas bama (Music ends) I call my work -- (Cheers, applause) Thank you. I call my work stage sculpture, but of course what's really being sculpted is the experience of the audience, and as directors and designers, we have to take responsibility for every minute that the audience spend with us. We're a bit like pilots navigating a flight path for a hundred thousand passengers. And in the case of the Canadian artist The Weeknd, we translated this flight path literally into an origami paper folding airplane that took off over the heads of the audience, broke apart in mid-flight, complications, and then rose out of the ashes restored at the end of the show. And like any flight, the most delicate part is the liftoff, the beginning, because when you design a pop concert, the prime material that you're working with is something that doesn't take trucks or crew to transport it. It doesn't cost anything, and yet it fills every atom of air in the arena, before the show starts. It's the audience's anticipation. Everyone brings with them the story of how they came to get there, the distances they traveled, the months they had to work to pay for the tickets. Sometimes they sleep overnight outside the arena, and our first task is to deliver for an audience on their anticipation, to deliver their first sight of the performer. When I work with men, they're quite happy to have their music transformed into metaphor -- spaceflights, mountains. But with women, we work a lot with masks and with three-dimensional portraiture, because the fans of the female artist crave her face. And when the audience arrived to see Adele's first live concert in five years, they were met with this image of her eyes asleep. If they listened carefully, they would hear her sleeping breath echoing around the arena, waiting to wake up. Here's how the show began. (Video: Cheers, applause) (Music) Adele: Hello. (Cheers, applause) Es Devlin: With U2, we're navigating the audience over a terrain that spans three decades of politics, poetry and music. And over many months, meeting with the band and their creative teams, this is the sketch that kept recurring, this line, this street, the street that connects the band's past with their present, the tightrope that they walk as activists and artists, a walk through cinema that allows the band to become protagonists in their own poetry. (Music: U2's "Where the Streets Have No Name") Bono: I wanna run I want to hide I wanna tear down the walls That hold me inside Es Devlin: The end of the show is like the end of a flight. It's an arrival. It's a transfer from the stage out to the audience. For the British band Take That, we ended the show by sending an 80-foot high mechanical human figure out to the center of the crowd. (Music) Like many translations from music to mechanics, this one was initially deemed entirely technically impossible. The first three engineers we took it to said no, and eventually, the way that it was achieved was by keeping the entire control system together while it toured around the country, so we had to fold it up onto a flatbed truck so it could tour around without coming apart. And of course, what this meant was that the dimension of its head was entirely determined by the lowest motorway bridge that it had to travel under on its tour. And I have to tell you that it turns out there is an unavoidable and annoyingly low bridge low bridge just outside Hamburg. (Laughter) (Music) Another of the most technically complex pieces that we've worked on is the opera "Carmen" at Bregenz Festival in Austria. We envisaged Carmen's hands rising out of Lake Constance, and throwing this deck of cards in the air and leaving them suspended between sky and sea. But this transient gesture, this flick of the wrists had to become a structure that would be strong enough to withstand two Austrian winters. So there's an awful lot that you don't see in this photograph that's working really hard. It's a lot of ballast and structure and support around the back, and I'm going to show you the photos that aren't on my website. They're photos of the back of a set, the part that's not designed for the audience to see, however much work it's doing. And you know, this is actually the dilemma for an artist who is working as a stage designer, because so much of what I make is fake, it's an illusion. And yet every artist works in pursuit of communicating something that's true. But we are always asking ourselves: "Can we communicate truth using things that are false?" And now when I attend the shows that I've worked on, I often find I'm the only one who is not looking at the stage. I'm looking at something that I find equally fascinating, and it's the audience. (Cheers) I mean, where else do you witness this: this many humans, connected, focused, undistracted and unfragmented? And lately, I've begun to make work that originates here, in the collective voice of the audience. "Poem Portraits" is a collective poem. It began at the Serpentine Gallery in London, and everybody is invited to donate one word to a collective poem. And instead of that large single LED portrait that was broadcasting to the back of the stadium, in this case, every member of the audience gets to take their own portrait home with them, and it's woven in with the words that they've contributed to the collective poem. So they keep a fragment of an ever-evolving collective work. And next year, the collective poem will take architectural form. This is the design for the UK Pavilion at the World Expo 2020. The UK ... In my lifetime, it's never felt this divided. It's never felt this noisy with divergent voices. And it's never felt this much in need of places where voices might connect and converge. And it's my hope that this wooden sculpture, this wooden instrument, a bit like that violin I used to play, might be a place where people can play and enter their word at one end of the cone, emerge at the other end of the building, and find that their word has joined a collective poem, a collective voice. (Music) These are simple experiments in machine learning. The algorithm that generates the collective poem is pretty simple. It's like predictive text, only it's trained on millions of words written by poets in the 19th century. So it's a sort of convergence of intelligence, past and present, organic and inorganic. And we were inspired by the words of Stephen Hawking. Towards the end of his life, he asked quite a simple question: If we as a species were ever to come across another advanced life-form, an advanced civilization, how would we speak to them? What collective language would we speak as a planet? The language of light reaches every audience. All of us are touched by it. None of us can hold it. And in the theater, we begin each work in a dark place, devoid of light. We stay up all night focusing the lights, programming the lights, trying to find new ways to sculpt and carve light. (Music) This is a portrait of our practice, always seeking new ways to shape and reshape light, always finding words for things that we no longer need to say. And I want to say that this, and everything that I've just shown you, no longer exists in physical form. (Music) In fact, most of what I've made over the last 25 years doesn't exist anymore. But our work endures in memories, in synaptic sculptures, in the minds of those who were once present in the audience. (Music) I once read that a poem learnt by heart is what you have left, what can't be lost, even if your house burns down and you've lost all your possessions. I want to end with some lines that I learnt by heart a long time ago. (Music) They're written by the English novelist E.M. Forster, in 1910, just a few years before Europe, my continent, (Music) began tearing itself apart. And his call to convergence still resonates through most of what we're trying to make now. (Music) "Only connect! That was the whole of her sermon. Only connect the prose and the passion, and both will be exalted, And human love will be seen at its height. Only connect! And live in fragments no longer." Thank you. (Applause)
a gran escala. Por lo general, se comienza con bocetos. Yo estaba esbozando este retrato de la artista, de 18 metros, móvil, listo para la transmisión, y luego rompí el papel en dos. Partí la máscara para tratar de llegar a la humanidad subyacente. Y una cosa es hacer bocetos, pero por supuesto traducir un boceto en un edificio de seis plantas que va de gira y debe transportarse requiere tres meses de trabajo incesante de unos ingenieros excepcionales, hasta que finalmente llegamos a Miami e inauguramos el show en abril de 2016. (Video: Ovación) (Música: "Formation", Beyoncé) Beyoncé: Todos Uds., haters, obsesionados con esa bobería illuminati. Paparazzi, capta mi vuelo y mi confiada frescura. Soy muy peligrosa cuando llevo puesto mi vestido Givenchy. Soy tan posesiva que luzco sus collares Roc. Mi papi es Alabama; mi mami, Louisiana. Mezcla ese negro con esa criolla, y tienes una rara mixtura texana (Fin de la música) Denomino a mi obra... (Ovación)(Aplausos) Gracias. Denomino a mi obra "escultura escénica", pero claro lo que se esculpe en realidad es la experiencia del público, y como directores y diseñadores, debemos asumir responsabilidad por cada minuto que el público pasa con nosotros. Somos un poco como pilotos que recorren una ruta aérea para cien mil pasajeros. Y en el caso del artista canadiense The Weeknd, tradujimos esta ruta de vuelo literalmente en un avión de origami de papel plegable que despegó sobre las cabezas del público, se destruyó en pleno vuelo, por complicaciones, para luego resurgir de las cenizas al final del espectáculo. Y como en todo vuelo, la parte más delicada es el despegue, el comienzo, porque cuando diseñas un concierto de pop, la materia prima con la que trabajas es algo que ni un camión, ni un equipo, pueden transportar. Y no tiene precio, e inunda cada átomo de aire antes que comience el show. Es la expectativa del público. Cada uno trae consigo la historia de cómo llegó hasta allí, las distancias que viajaron, los meses que tuvieron que trabajar para pagar las entradas. A veces pasan la noche fuera del estadio, y nuestra primera tarea es colmar las expectativas del público, brindarles un primer contacto memorable con la artista. Cuando trabajo con hombres, ellos están felices de ver transformar su música en metáfora... vuelos espaciales, montañas. Pero con las mujeres, trabajamos mucho con máscaras y retratos tridimensionales, porque los fans de la artista femenina anhelan su rostro. Y cuando el público llegó a ver el primer concierto en vivo de Adele en cinco años, se encontraron con esta imagen de sus ojos dormidos. Si escuchaban atentamente, oían su aliento dormido haciendo eco por todo el estadio, esperando a despertar. Así comenzó el espectáculo. (Video: Ovación, Aplausos) (Música) Adele: Hola. (Ovación)(Aplausos) Es Devlin: Con U2, estamos navegando por la audiencia sobre un terreno que abarca tres décadas de política, poesía y música. Y durante muchos meses, al reunirnos con la banda y sus equipos creativos, el boceto recurrente era el siguiente: esta línea, esta calle, la calle que une el pasado de la banda con su presente, la cuerda floja por la que caminan como activistas y artistas, un paseo por el cine que permite que la banda se convierta en protagonista de su propia poesía. (Música: "Where the Streets Have No Name", de U2) Bono: Quiero correr Quiero esconderme Quiero demoler las paredes Que me esconden Es Devlin: El final del espectáculo es como el final de un vuelo. Es una llegada. Es una transferencia del escenario al público. Para la banda británica Take That finalizamos el espectáculo enviando una figura humana mecánica de 24 metros hacia el centro de la multitud. (Música) Como muchas traducciones de música a mecánica, esta al principio parecía técnicamente imposible. Los primeros tres ingenieros consultados dijeron que no, hasta que al final se logró manteniendo todo el sistema de control junto mientras recorría el país, así que tuvimos que plegarlo en un camión de plataforma para poder transportarlo sin tener que desmontarlo. Y, por supuesto, eso significó que la dimensión de la cabeza estuvo determinada completamente por el puente de la autopista más bajo que tuvo que recorrer en la gira. Y debo decirles que resulta que hay un puente ineludible y fastidiosamente bajo en las afueras de Hamburgo. (Risas) (Música) Otra de las piezas más complejas técnicamente en las que hemos trabajado es la ópera "Carmen" en el Festival de Bregenz en Austria. Imaginamos las manos de Carmen salir del lago Constanza, lanzando esta baraja de cartas al aire dejándolas suspendidas entre el cielo y el mar. Pero este gesto transitorio, este movimiento de muñecas, tenía que convertirse en una estructura lo suficientemente fuerte para soportar dos inviernos austríacos. Así que hay una gran cantidad de cosas que no se ven en esta fotografía que implica verdadero trabajo. Hay gran cantidad de lastre y estructura y soporte en la parte posterior, y les voy a mostrar las fotos que no están en mi sitio web. Son fotos de la parte trasera del set, la parte pensada para que el público no la vea, por mucho trabajo que implique. Y este es el verdadero dilema de un artista que trabaja en la escenografía, porque gran parte de lo que hago es falso, es una ilusión. Y, sin embargo, cada artista trabaja en la búsqueda de comunicar algo verdadero. Pero siempre nos preguntamos: "¿Podemos comunicar la verdad mediante cosas falsas?" Cuando voy a un espectáculo en el que he trabajado, a menudo descubro que soy la única que no mira el escenario. Miro algo que me parece igualmente fascinante, y es el público. (Ovación) Quiero decir, ¿dónde más eres testigo de esto? Tantas personas, conectadas, concentradas, sin distracciones y sin fragmentación. Y últimamente, he empezado a hacer obras que se originan aquí, en la voz colectiva del público. "Poem Portraits" es un poema colectivo. Comenzó en Serpentine Gallery en Londres, donde todos están invitados a donar una palabra a un poema colectivo. Y en lugar de ese gran retrato de LED transmitido al fondo del estadio, en este caso, cada miembro del público puede llevarse a casa su propio retrato, y está entretejido con las palabras con las que han contribuido al poema colectivo. De modo que conservan un fragmento de una obra colectiva en constante evolución. Y el próximo año el poema colectivo tendrá forma arquitectónica. Este es el diseño para el Pabellón del Reino Unido en la Expo Mundial 2020. El Reino Unido... En toda mi vida nunca se sintió tan dividido. Nunca han sido tan atronadoras las voces divergentes. Nunca ha habido tanta necesidad de encontrar lugares donde las voces puedan conectarse y converger. Y espero que esta escultura de madera, este instrumento de madera, un poco como el violín que solía tocar, pueda ser un lugar donde la gente pueda jugar y contribuir con su palabra en un extremo del cono, salir en el otro extremo del edificio, y encontrar que su palabra se ha unido a un poema colectivo, a una voz colectiva. (Música) Son experimentos simples de aprendizaje automático. El algoritmo que genera el poema colectivo es bastante simple. Es como un texto predictivo entrenado con millones de palabras escritas por poetas en el siglo XIX. Es una especie de convergencia de inteligencia, pasada y presente, orgánica e inorgánica. Y nos inspiramos en las palabras de Stephen Hawking. Hacia el final de su vida hizo una pregunta bastante simple: Si como especie alguna vez encontramos otra forma de vida avanzada, una civilización avanzada, ¿cómo les hablaríamos? ¿Qué lenguaje colectivo hablaríamos como planeta? El lenguaje de la luz llega a todo público. A todos nos conmueve. Nadie puede contenerse. Y en el teatro, comenzamos cada obra en un lugar oscuro, sin luz. Nos quedamos despiertos toda la noche enfocando las luces, programándolas, tratando de encontrar nuevas formas de esculpir la luz. (Música) Este es un retrato de nuestra práctica. Siempre buscando nuevas formas de formar y reformar la luz, siempre buscando palabras para cosas que ya no necesitamos decir. Y quiero decir que esto, y todo lo que acabo de mostrar, ya no existe en forma física. (Música) De hecho, la mayor parte de lo que he hecho en los últimos 25 años ya no existe. Pero nuestro trabajo perdura en los recuerdos, en las esculturas sinápticas, en la mente de quienes estuvieron presentes una vez entre el público. (Música) Una vez leí que un poema aprendido de memoria es algo que queda, que no se puede perder, incluso si nuestra casa se incendia y uno pierde todas sus posesiones. Quiero finalizar con unas líneas que aprendí de memoria hace mucho tiempo. (Música) Fueron escritas por el novelista inglés E. M. Forster, en 1910, pocos años antes de que Europa, mi continente, (Música) empezara a desgarrarse. Y su llamado a la convergencia aún resuena en la mayor parte de lo que tratamos de hacer ahora. (Música) "¡Solo construir el puente! Ese era todo el sermón. Solo construir un puente entre la prosa y la pasión, y ambas resurgirán y el amor humano brillará en su cima. ¡Solo construir el puente! No más vida fragmentaria". Gracias. (Aplausos)